[Music]
hello and welcome to this session on
what's new in opening Visual Studio code
from uh the web client it's a feature
which is relevant both for developers as
well as consultants and support teams
for investigating and troubleshooting
issues I'm Peter boring and with me
today I have Blanca roblo and so
tonas in this session we're going to
talk about new abilities for creating
launch configurations and opening
extensions from the client as well as
searching symbols uh once inside of
visous Studio code for instance to
investigate or to use it as a context
for GitHub co-pilot but first let's have
a small recap of the overall
feature so some releases ago we
introduced the powerful ability uh to
invoke opening Vis Studio code from
within the web client this removed
manual work and lowered the barrier for
connecting a visual studio code to an
environment
supporting increasing the developer
productivity empowering tech servy
consultants to investigate and do light
troubleshooting uh with limited Visual
Studio code knowledge and it also
empowers support to troubleshoot faster
and lower time to
mitigate so what did we
add to make it much easier to debug a
specific environment we added an attach
option in the help and support page back
in 23 release Wave 2 this supports
debugging in sandboxes as well as
capturing snapshots and profile
performance issues both in sandbox
environments but also in production
environments in that release we also
added the ability to quickly go to
source code uh if available for pages
and table Fields directly from within
the page inspector on a page then in the
last release we added the the ability to
open extension source code uh when it
has a link to a git repo for instance as
a result of building it in an algo for
GitHub pipeline um and hopefully you're
using this or another devop solution to
automate and streamline your development
and deployment life
cycle if you want to know more about
these features watch the launch event
sessions that we did on uh this in uh
2023 relas Wave 2 and 2024 release Wave
2 um and we'll provide links uh at in
the description for this video so what
have we added in this release Blanca can
you tell us
more all right so thank you Peter now
let's dive into the features that have
been added in this release so we
actually have three new capabilities to
the open MBS code functionality and this
come as a result from the feedback that
we have received from J so please please
keep that coming and we can make some
new
features um so these new three features
are first of all we have added the
ability to generate launch
configurations that match your
environment directly from H help and
support and also extension
management we have also added the
ability to go to extension management
select the extensions that you want and
then formatted format them as
dependencies so then you can use them
across your projects or just share them
and then along that same line we have H
also add the ability to H download those
selected dependencies directly on your
vs code project so then you can have the
symbols already on your vs Cod project
with a single
click so looking a bit closer into the
generate launch configurations um action
this is an action that again is in help
and support and uh extension management
and when you click on that then what it
does is that on your vs code project it
either creates or updates your launch
configurations to match uh your
environment so you don't have to edit
any of the parameters and with this you
can already if you have a sbox emance
you have the configurations to publish
and attach debugger since these are only
available for sbox environments and then
you can also have the configurations to
download symbols and snapshot debug
that's both for sandbox and production
environments next up for the next
capability if you go to extension
management you can just select some
extensions and you can just click on
show and copy and what this will do is
just create a um popup like this so you
can have H your extensions and view them
as dependences and you can just copy
that use it on your project or just J
share it with other developers and use
it for example to travel shoot um your
environment and then last of all we have
also added the ability to uh once you
select this extensions if you want them
directly on your vs code project then
you can just click on downloading vs
code and this will download the
extensions on your vco project so you
can also get started to code against
them and use them as references or you
can just go ahead and explore what what
are what is the code for those
extensions
like so that was it for the new
capabilities now let's go ahead and see
them in
action yeah so this is my new preview
envir M and I want to get started and
develop an extension here on this new
version or I just want to test my
existing Solutions on the new
environment so instead of having to go
to vs code and updating my H
configurations I can do that with a
simple click if I go to help and
support then I will find this new action
generate launch configurations for this
environment and I can just go ahead and
click on that and this will open yes
code
and it will also generate in this case
because I didn't have one already a new
project from scratch and if I look into
my launch configurations I see they're
already already there they are
autogenerated to match the parameters
from my environment so I didn't have to
do absolutely nothing here and I'm
already I have a project already ready
to for example publish or download
symbols with these
configurations so again that was super
simple way to get started
now let's say my project also depends on
some other extensions and I want to code
against them and I want to reference
them so again in that in instead of
going to my vs code project having to go
to map. Json and having to manually
enter all this information about the
extensions H I can just simply go to
extension
management I can just select the
extensions that I want to use in my
project so let's say for
example this over here and then I can
just go to developing this code get
selected as
dependencies let's say I want to show
and copy in this case I already see this
text um which I can just go ahead copy
it and put it in my project or if I
already want this in my project then I
can just go ahead and click downloading
vs code and again this will lead me back
to my vs code project and then if I
inspect my app. Json I see all of these
dependencies have already been entered
into my project and I also see that they
are being downloaded um so if I look at
my Al packages I already have the
symbols for these
extensions um so I can I can already get
started and code against them or if I
want I can also go ahead and explore
what's in this extensions of course
that's if the IP um of the partner
permits that and luckily um we have also
added the ability to explore the is in
vs code and that's something that shis
will show us next thank you very much
blancco let's dive right into it uh I'm
going to show you a feature we have
added that lets you figure out exactly
what is inside your dependencies in
terms of um available tables um pages
and so on so let's suppose I am
developing a new uh extension and I want
to use the number series functionality
and I want to see what is available in
terms of number series I can use the
combination Control Plus T which is go
to symbol in vs code and try to figure
out uh what is available for number
series what I just need to do here is to
do number series and then you will see
we get results from all of our
dependencies on number series I can just
navigate directly to the page for the
number series and figure out exactly
what is inside it through the symbols
this works for symbols which are coming
from your apps and Microsoft as well as
long as the source code is available to
debug now let's look at another very
good use of
this this can also be used in tandem
with
copilot let's try to use for example
copilot to ask some questions about the
customer table
if I go to copilot and I ask it what is
in the customer
table then what I will see is copilot
doesn't really know what is the customer
table because it doesn't have it in
context so symbols allows us to give
this required context to answer this
question what I can do is that uh I can
go here and I can
say what
fields are in
the and I can use this special keyword
symbol and search for the customer
table now by clicking
here copilot gets access to the customer
table and it is able to use it to inform
the answer that is going to give us so
now copilot has the available context to
answer us exactly What fields are inside
the customer
table and it doesn't need access to the
entire seource code in order to provide
this even just having the symbols
available will give it a much more
informed answer rather than uh if you it
didn't have the context at all so it is
a very powerful tool to use to uh help
you collaborate with copilot effectively
thank you very much thank you sus so
that's all thanks for joining this
session and staying to the end uh I hope
you enjoyed the improvements uh that we
made to make it easier to open Vis
Studio code from uh the web client
whether to investigate troubleshoot or
develop against one or more extensions
uh in the environment so you can even
access source code uh if the Publishers
has granted you that via their um IP
resource protection policy enjoy the
rest of the launch sessions thank you